Guide to the Richard Southall Papers
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Richard Southall papers
1981-1986
SC1002
Southall, Richard
1.5 Linear feet
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Provenance
Materials were the gift of Richard Southall, 2010.
Information about Access
Open for research. Audio-visual materials are not available in original format, and must be reformatted to a digital use copy.
Biographical Note
Richard Southall, lecturer in the Department of Typography and Graphic Communication at the University of Reading, England, worked with Donald Knuth at Stanford between 1983 and 1986 on the Metafont Project.
Scope and Contents note
These papers pertain to Southall’s work on METAFONT and fall into four broad categories. The first concerns 'the CMR project': the revision undertaken by Southall and Stanford Prof D. E. Knuth in March and April 1982 of Knuth’s original design for the bold sanserif variant of the Computer Modern family of typefaces. The second consists of notes, teaching material, and products from the course in METAFONT programming (CS279) that was given at Stanford in the summer of 1984 to introduce the new version of the METAFONT language. The third category of material consists of notes and correspondence relating to the work of the digital typography group at Stanford from late 1983 until the beginning of the CS279 course in 1984. The fourth comprises development material, program listings, and tests for the two versions (known as TKMF and NMT) of Southall’s own METAFONT font typeface design. This was begun in late 1983, revised in 1984 with the appearance of the new METAFONT, continued at the Université Louis-Pasteur in Strasbourg in the summer of 1985, and eventually abandoned owing to the necessity for Southall to complete his report "Designing new typefaces with METAFONT" (STAN-CS-85-1074) before leaving his post at Stanford.
Access Terms
Knuth, Donald Ervin, 1938-; Computer fonts.; METAFONT (Computer system).; Type and type-founding--Data processing.
Collection Contents
- The CMR project files, 1981-1982; 15 folder(s)
  - Correspondence between RS and M. Wrolstad, editor of "Visible language", concerning article by Knuth in that journal, and between RS and Donald E. Knuth, concerning RS's visits to Stanford in 1981 and 1982, 1981-1982 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Notes by RS made during his first visit to Stanford, March - April, 1981-1982 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Printouts of Scott Kim's programs for his Euler characters (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Knuth’s articles and responses to (photocopies) (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Computer Modern and Monotype Modern Series 8A typefaces: originals, photographs, enlargements and paste-ups (Box 1, Folder 5-6)
  - RS's redesign of Computer Modern Sanserif Bold: test xeroxes (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - RS's redesign of Computer Modern Sanserif Bold: proofs, small letters (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - RS's redesign of Computer Modern Sanserif Bold: canon tests (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - RS's redesign of Computer Modern Sanserif Bold: drawings (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - RS's redesign of Computer Modern Sanserif Bold: development series (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - RS's redesign of Computer Modern Sanserif Bold: early work (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - RS's redesign of Computer Modern Sanserif Bold: alphatype tests (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - RS's redesign of Computer Modern Sanserif Bold: current proofs (caps) (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - RS's redesign of Computer Modern Sanserif Bold: miscellaneous proofs (Box 1, Folder 15)
- TK design files, 1984 and undated; 6 folder(s)
  - Proof mode and smokes (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Smokes (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Proof mode (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Type proofs (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - RS drawings (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Computer printout, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- CS279 Metafont programming class files, 1984; 3 folder(s)
  - Handouts and teaching materials (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Printout of original version of "font1" program (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Class picnic arrangements and proofs of ornaments produced by students (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Digital Typography Group at Stanford, 1983-1984; 2 folder(s)
  - RS’s teaching notes; notes and memoranda of the group; program listings for RS’s designs (Box 2, Folder 10-11)
- Metafont Work by Richard Southall, 1983-1986; 8 folder(s)
  - "Making a typeface with new Metafont" talk given to the TeX User Group meeting, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Drawings, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Illustrations for TUG [piece?], 1985 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - TSA’s [Tamil?] – program list and examples, undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Drawings, proofs, and program listings of the 1983-84 version of the TKMF design, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Drawings, proofs, and program listings of the 1983-84 version of the TKMF design, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Printouts and drawings of RS’s NMT design, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - RS’s Metafont working notes at Stanford and Strasbourg, 1985 April-1986 December (Box 3, Folder 6)